<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sqlite on Anton Zhiyanov</title><link>https://antonz.org/tags/sqlite/</link><description>Recent content in sqlite on Anton Zhiyanov</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 10:40:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://antonz.org/tags/sqlite/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SQLite playground in the browser</title><link>https://antonz.org/sqlite-playground/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 10:40:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://antonz.org/sqlite-playground/</guid><description>What I&amp;rsquo;ve always lacked is something similar to JSFiddle, but for SQLite. An online playground to quickly test an SQL query and share it with others.
Here is what I wanted:
Binary database import, not just SQL schema. Support both local and remote databases (by url). Save the database and queries in the cloud. Free of charge, no sign-up required. The latest version of SQLite. Minimalistic and mobile friendly. So I&amp;rsquo;ve built SQLime — an online SQLite playground for debugging and sharing SQL snippets.</description></item><item><title>SQLite is not a toy database</title><link>https://antonz.org/sqlite-is-not-a-toy-database/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://antonz.org/sqlite-is-not-a-toy-database/</guid><description>English • Russian • Spanish
Whether you are a developer, data analyst, QA engineer, DevOps person, or product manager - SQLite is a perfect tool for you. Here is why.
A few well-known facts to get started:
SQLite is the most common DBMS in the world, shipped with all popular operating systems. SQLite is serverless. For developers, SQLite is embedded directly into the app. For everyone else, there is a convenient database console (REPL), provided as a single file (sqlite3.</description></item><item><title>How to create a 1M record table with a single query</title><link>https://antonz.org/random-table/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://antonz.org/random-table/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to check how a query behaves on a large table - but there is no such table at hand. This is not a problem if your DBMS supports SQL recursion: lots of data can be generated with a single query. The WITH RECURSIVE clause comes to the rescue.
I&amp;rsquo;m going to use SQLite, but the same (or similar) queries will work for PostgreSQL and other DBMSs. Specifically, WITH RECURSIVE is supported in MariaDB 10.</description></item><item><title>SQLite is not so easy to compile</title><link>https://antonz.org/sqlite-is-not-so-easy-to-compile/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 11:45:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://antonz.org/sqlite-is-not-so-easy-to-compile/</guid><description>SQLite shell is quite easy to compile, right?
curl -L http://sqlite.org/2021/sqlite-amalgamation-3350000.zip --output src.zip unzip src.zip mv sqlite-amalgamation-3350000 src gcc src/shell.c src/sqlite3.c -o sqlite3 -lpthread -ldl Well, unless you want all the cool features which are not included in the default build. Or unless you are using Windows and prefer 64-bit binary to 32-bit. Or unless you do not have gcc installed.
I found myself in these situations a couple of times.</description></item><item><title>What's new in SQLite 3.35</title><link>https://antonz.org/sqlite-3-35/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 19:10:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://antonz.org/sqlite-3-35/</guid><description>SQLite developers often prefer to work on database internals. For an external observer nothing really changes. 2020 was a pleasant exception - SQLite received a bunch of nice features for ordinary users, such as generated columns, UPDATE FROM and fantastic .mode box in the shell.
There&amp;rsquo;s every chance that 2021 will continue the tradition. Here&amp;rsquo;s what shipped in the 3.35 release today:
Math functions ‼️ Column removal ❗ RETURNING processed rows for DELETE, INSERT and UPDATE.</description></item></channel></rss>